So, I have an overlooked but potentially lucrative
حسنا، أقدم لكم فرصة استثمار
investment opportunity for you.
يغض الناس الطرف عنها ولكنها مربحة.
Over the past 10 years in the UK,
خلال السنين العشر الماضية في بريطانيا،
the return on burial plots has outperformed the UK property market
العائد من قطع الأراضي المخصصة كمدافن فاق أداء سوق العقارات في بريطانيا
by a ratio of around three to one.
بنسبة تعادل ثلاثة إلى واحد.
There are private cemeteries being set up with plots for sale to investors,
توجد مدافن خاصة تتوفر فيها قطع للبيع للمستثمرين،
and they start at around 3,900 pounds.
تبدأ من 3900 جنيه.
And they're projected to achieve about 40 percent growth.
ومن المتوقع أن تحقق نموًا يعادل 40%.
The biggest advantage is that this is a market with continuous demand.
الميزة الكبرى هي أن هذا يعتبر سوقا ذو طلب دائم.
Now, this is a real proposition,
الآن، هذا اقتراح جدِّي،
and there are companies out there that really are offering this investment,
وهناك العديد من الشركات التي تقدم مثل هذا الإستثمار،
but my interest in it is quite different.
ولكن ما يثير اهتمامي بالأمر مختلف تمامًا.
I'm an architect and urban designer,
أنا معمارية ومصممة في المناطق الحضرية،
and for the past year and a half,
وخلال السنة والنصف المنصرمة،
I've been looking at approaches to death and dying
بدأت أهتم بأمر الموت والفناء
and at how they've shaped our cities and the buildings within them.
وكيف أن هذا الأمر قد شكَّل مدننا وما تحويه من مباني.
So in the summer, I did my first exhibition
لذلك في الصيف، أقمت معرضي الأول
on death and architecture in Venice,
عن العلاقة بين الموت والمعمار في مدينة البندقية،
and it was called "Death in Venice."
وقد سمّي "الموت في مدينة البندقية."
And because death is a subject
وبما أن الموت يعتبر من المواضيع التي
that many of us find quite uncomfortable to talk about,
يشعر أغلبنا بعدم الراحة حين الحديث عنه،
the exhibition was designed to be quite playful,
تم تصميم المعرض بحيث يكون هزليًا إلى حد بعيد،
so that people would literally engage with it.
حتى يتمكن الناس حرفيًا من التفاعل معه.
So one of our exhibits was an interactive map of London
فقد كان أحد عروضنا هو خريطة تفاعلية لمدينة لندن
which showed just how much of the real estate in the city
والتي أوضحت كم العقارات في المدينة التي
is given over to death.
يتم تخصيصها كمدافن.
As you wave your hand across the map,
فبينما تشير بيدك على الخريطة،
the name of the piece of real estate -- the building or the cemetery --
يتم الكشف عن اسم العقار
is revealed.
أو المبنى أو المقبرة.
And those white shapes that you can see,
وهذه الأِشكال البيضاء التي ترونها،
they're all of the hospitals and hospices
ترمز جميعها إلى المستشفيات ودور العجزة
and mortuaries and cemeteries in the city.
والمشارح والمقابر في المدينة.
In fact, the majority are cemeteries.
في الحقيقة، السواد الأعظم منها مقابر.
We wanted to show that, even though death and burial are things
أردنا أن نلفت الإنتباه أنه برغم أن الموت وعمليات الدفن تعتبر أشياء
that we might not think about,
قد نمتنع عن التفكير فيها،
they're all around us, and they're important parts of our cities.
إلا أنها في كل مكان حولنا، وتعتبر أجزاء مهمة من مدننا.
So about half a million people die in the UK each year,
يموت حوالي النصف مليون شخص في المملكة المتحدة سنويا،
and of those, around a quarter will want to be buried.
وبالنسبة لهذا العدد، سيود ربعهم أن يتم دفنهم.
But the UK, like many Western European countries,
ولكن المملكة المتحدة، مثلها مثل العديد من دول غرب أوروبا،
is running out of burial space,
بدأت تَنْفَدُ فيها المساحات المخصصة للدفن،
especially in the major cities.
وبخاصة في المدن الكبيرة.
And the Greater London Authority has been aware of this for a while,
وقد وعت سلطة مدينة لندن الكبرى لهذا الأمر منذ مدة،
and the main causes are population growth,
والأسباب الرئيسية لذلك هي النمو السكاني،
the fact that existing cemeteries are almost full.
وحقيقة أن المقابر الموجودة حاليا مليئة بالكامل.
There's a custom in the UK that graves are considered to be occupied forever,
هناك عرف في المملكة المتحدة أن المقابر تعتبر شاغرة للأبد،
and there's also development pressure -- people want to use that same land
وهناك أيضا ضغط النمو، حيث يريد الناس استخدام نفس هذه الأراضي
to build houses or offices or shops.
لبناء المنازل أو المكاتب أو المحلات التجارية.
So they came up with a few solutions.
لذلك جادت قريحتهم ببعض الحلول.
They were like, well, maybe we can reuse those graves after 50 years.
فقد كان لسان حالهم، حسنا، ربما نتمكن من اعادة استخدام هذه المقابر بعد 50 عامًا.
Or maybe we can bury people, like, four deep,
أو ربما قد ندفن الموتى في شكل أربعة طوابق،
so that four people can be buried in the same plot,
وبذلك ندفن أربعة أشخاص في نفس قطعة الأرض،
and we can make more efficient use of the land that way,
وبهذه الطريقة نحقق الاستخدام الأمثل لهذه الأراضي،
and in that way, hopefully London will still have space to bury people
وهكذا، ستتوفر مساحة لدفن الموتى في مدينة لندن
in the near future.
في المستقبل القريب.
But, traditionally, cemeteries haven't been taken care of
ولكن، وعلى نحو تقليدي، لا يتم الاهتمام بالمقابر
by the local authority.
من قبل السلطة المحلية.
In fact, the surprising thing is that there's no legal obligation
في الحقيقة، الشيء المثير للدهشة هو أنه لا يوجد الزام قانوني
on anyone in the UK to provide burial space.
على أي شخص في المملكة المتحدة لتوفير مساحة للدفن.
Traditionally, it's been done by private and religious organizations,
تقليديًا، يتم القيام بذلك من قبل منظمات خاصة ودينية،
like churches and mosques and synagogues.
مثل الكنائس والمساجد والمعابد.
But there's also occasionally been a for-profit group
وهناك أيضًا مجموعة ربحية
who has wanted to get in on the act.
والتي أرادت القيام بهذا الأمر.
And, you know, they look at the small size of a burial plot
وكما تعلمون، فهم ينظرون إلى الحيز الصغير لمساحة قطعة الدفن
and that high cost,
والسعر المرتفع،
and it looks like there's serious money to be made.
ويبدو أن الأمر مربح جدًا
So, actually, if you want to go out and start your own cemetery,
لذلك، في الواقع، إذا ما أردت البدء بانشاء مقبرتك الخاصة،
you kind of can.
فإنه يمكنك ذلك.
There was this couple in South Wales,
هذان الزوجان في جنوب ويلز،
and they had a farmhouse and a load of fields next to it,
كانا يملكان بيتا ريفيا والعديد من الحقول بجانبه،
and they wanted to develop the land.
وأراد القيام بتطوير الأرض.
They had a load of ideas.
كانت أذهانهما مثقلة بالأفكار.
They first thought about making a caravan park,
فكرا في بادئ الأمر بانشاء حديقة للمنازل المتنقلة،
but the council said no.
ولكن المجلس رفض طلبهما.
And then they wanted to make a fish farm
ثم أرادا عمل مزرعة أسماك
and again the council said no.
ومجددًا رفض المجلس طلبهما.
Then they hit on the idea of making a cemetery
ثم برقت في أذهانهما فكرة بناء مقبرة
and they calculated that by doing this,
وقد قاما بحساب ذلك بعمل التالي،
they could increase the value of their land
بامكانهما زيادة قيمة أرضهما
from about 95,000 pounds to over one million pounds.
من حوالي 95000 جنيه إلى أكثر من مليون من الجنيهات.
But just to come back to this idea of making profit from cemeteries,
بالعودة إلى فكرة جني أرباح من بناء المقابر،
like, it's kind of ludicrous, right?
إنه شيئ غريب بعض الشيء، أليس كذلك؟
The thing is that the high cost of those burial plots
الشيئ الجدير بالذكر هو أن السعر المرتفع لهذه الأراضي المعدة للدفن
is actually very misleading.
هو في الواقع مضلل جدًا.
They look like they're expensive,
فهي تبدو غالية الثمن،
but that cost reflects the fact that you need to maintain the burial plot --
ولكن ذلك السعر يعكس حقيقة أنك بحاجة للحفاظ على قطعة الدفن تلك
like, someone has to cut the grass for the next 50 years.
مثل شخص يتوجب عليه تشذيب العشب للخمسين سنة القادمة.
That means it's very difficult to make money from cemeteries.
ذلك يعني أنه من الصعب جدًا جني المال من بناء المقابر.
And it's the reason that normally they're run by the council
وهو السبب في أنه عادة يتم تسييرها من قبل المجلس
or by a not-for-profit group.
أو من قبل مجموعة غير ربحية.
But anyway, the council granted these people permission,
ولكن على أي حال، منحهما المجلس إذنًا ببدء العمل،
and they're now trying to build their cemetery.
وهم الآن يحاولان بناء مقبرتهما الخاصة.
So just to explain to you kind of how this works:
لذا كي أوضح لكم بعض الشيء كيف يعمل هذا الأمر:
If I want to build something in the UK,
إذا ما أردت بناء شيء في المملكة المتحدة،
like a cemetery for example,
مثل مقبرة على سبيل المثال،
then I have to apply for planning permission first.
يتوجب على أولًا التقدم لاستلام إذن تخطيط.
So if I want to build a new office building for a client
فإذا ما أردت بناء مبنى مكتبي جديد لعميل ما
or if I want to extend my home
أو إذا ما كنت أرغب في تمديد بيتي
or, you know, if I have a shop and I want to convert it into an office,
أو كما تعلمون، إذا ما كنت أملك متجرا وأريد تحويله إلى مكتب،
and I submit them to the council for permission.
وأن اسلمها للمجلس بغرض الموافقة.
And they'll look at things like how it fits in the surroundings.
وسيركزون على أشياء من قبيل مدى تناسبها مع المواقع المحيطة.
So they'll look at what it looks like.
لذا سيركزون على ما ستبدو عليه.
But they'll also think about things like what impact is it going to have
وسيفكرون كذلك في ما هو التأثير الذي ستتركه
on the local environment?
على البيئة المحلية؟
And they'll be thinking about things like,
وسيفكرون في أشياء مثل،
is this thing going to cause pollution
هل سيسبب هذا الشيء تلوثًا بيئيًا
or is there going to be a lot of traffic
أو هل سيحدث أزمة مرورية
that wants to go to this thing that I've built?
بسبب هذا الشيء الذي بنيته؟
But also good things.
ولكن هناك أخبارًا جيدة.
Is it going to add local services like shops to the neighborhood
هل ستضيف خدمات محلية مثل المتاجر للحي
that local people would like to use?
الذي قد يستخدمه السكان المحلييون؟
And they'll weigh up the advantages and the disadvantages
ثم سيزنون المحاسن والمساوئ المترتبة على ذلك
and they'll make a decision.
ومن بعدها يتخذون قرارهم.
So that's how it works if I want to build a large cemetery.
إذا هكذا تجري الأمور إذا ما أردت بناء مقبرة ضخمة.
But what if I've got a piece of land
ولكن ماذا إذا ما كنت أمتلك قطعة أرض صغيرة
and I just want to bury a few people, like five or six?
وأريد فقط أن أدفن فيها بعض الأشخاص، خمسة أو ستة أشخاص؟
Well, then -- actually, I don't need permission from anyone!
حسنا، في الواقع حينها لست بحاجة إلى إذن من أي كان!
There's actually almost no regulation in the UK around burial,
في واقع الأمر ليس هناك من قيد في المملكة المتحدة حول الدفن،
and the little bit that there is, is about not polluting water courses,
و القيل الموجود منها بهدف منع تلويث المجاري المائية،
like not polluting rivers or groundwater.
مثل منع تلويث الأنهار والمياه الجوفية
So actually, if you want to go and make your own mini-cemetery,
لذلك إذا ما أردت بناء مقبرتك الخاصة بشكل مصغر
then you can.
فإن ذلك أمر سهل.
But I mean, like -- really, who does this? Right?
ولكني أقصد، من يفعل هذا حقا؟ أليس كذلك؟
Well, if you're an aristocratic family and you have a large estate,
حسنا، إذا ما كنت تنتمي لعائلة أرستقراطية وتمتلك عقارا ضخمًا،
then there's a chance that you'll have a mausoleum on it,
إذا هنالك فرصة أن يكون لك ضريح فيه،
and you'll bury your family there.
كما ستدفن عائلتك فيه أيضًا.
But the really weird thing
ولكن الشيء الغريب حقا
is that you don't need to have a piece of land of a certain size
هو أنك لست بحاجة لامتلاك قطعة أرض ذات مساحة محددة
before you're allowed to start burying people on it.
قبل أن يسمح لك بالبدء بدفن الناس فيها.
And so that means that, technically,
وذلك فنيًا يعني،
this applies to, like, the back garden of your house in the suburbs.
أن هذا ينطبق على الحديقة الخلفية لمنزلك في ضاحية المدينة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what if you wanted to try this yourself at home?
إذا، ماذا لو أردت أن تعيش التجربة بنفسك في المنزل؟
Well, there's a few councils that have guidance on their website
حسنا، هناك بعض المجالس يوفرون دليلًا على مواقعهم الإلكترونية
which can help you.
والتي تقدم لك بعض المساعدة.
So, the first thing that they tell you
أول مايخبرونك به
is that you need to have a certificate of burial before you can go ahead --
أنك بحاجة لشهادة دفن قبل أن تتمكن من فعل ذلك
you're not allowed to just murder people and put them under the patio.
إذ ليس من المسموح أن تقتل الناس ثم تدفنهم في الباحة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They also tell you that you need to keep a record of where the grave is.
كذلك يتوجب عليك أن تحتفظ بسجل يوضح مكان القبر.
But that's pretty much it for formal requirements.
ولكن ذلك كثير جدًا بالنسبة لمتطلبات رسمية.
Now, they do warn you that your neighbors might not like this,
الآن، سيحذرونك بأن جيرانك قد لا يحبذون هذا الأمر،
but, legally speaking, there's almost nothing that they can do about it.
ولكن، من ناحية قانونية، ليس بوسعهم فعل شيء حيال هذا الأمر.
And just in case any of you still had that profit idea in your mind
وفي حال ما كانت تدور في ذهن أحدكم تلك الفكرة الربحية
about how much those burial plots cost
عن كم تكلف هذه الأراضي المخصصة للدفن
and how much money you might be able to make,
وكم مقدار الربح الذي من المتوقع أن تجنيه،
they also warn that it might cause the value of your house
كذلك يحذرونك أنه نتيجة لذلك قد تنخفض قيمة منزلك
to drop by 20 percent.
بمعدل 20%.
Although, actually, it's more likely
على الرغم من أنه، من المتوقع جدًا
that no one will want to buy your house at all after that.
أنه لن يود أحد ما على الإطلاق شراء منزلك بعد كل هذا.
So what I find fascinating about this
لذلك فإن ما أجده رائعًا حيال هذا الأمر
is the fact that it kind of sums up many of our attitudes towards death.
هو حقيقة أن هذا الشيء يلخص نوعًا ما سلوكنا تجاه الموت.
In the UK, and I think that the figures across Europe are probably similar,
في المملكة المتحدة، وأظن أن الأرقام حول أوروبا مشابهة لذلك،
only about 30 percent of people have ever talked to anyone
30% فقط من الناس تحدثوا إلى شخص ما
about their wishes around death,
عن أمنياتهم المتعلقة بالموت،
and even for people over 75,
وحتى بالنسبة لمن تجاوزوا سن 75 سنة،
only 45 percent of people have ever talked about this.
45% فقط تناولوا أمر الموت في أحاديثهم.
And the reasons that people give ... you know,
والأسباب كما تعلمون،
they think that their death is far off
هو أنهم يظنون أن موتهم شيء بعيد الحدوث
or they think that they're going to make people uncomfortable
أو أنهم يظنون أنهم سيتسببون بمضايقة الناس
by talking about it.
إذا ما تحدثوا عن هذا الأمر.
And you know, to a certain extent,
وكما تعلمون، إلى حد ما،
there are other people out there who are taking care of things for us.
هناك أشخاص من حولنا يهتمون بالأشياء من أجلنا.
The government has all this regulation and bureaucracy around things
للحكومة قوانين وبيروقراطية متعلقة بالأشياء
like burying a death, for example,
مثل دفن الموتى على سبيل المثال،
and there's people like funeral directors
وهناك أشخاص يعملون كمديري جنازات
who devote their entire working lives to this issue.
حيث كرَّسوا مجمل حياتهم العملية من أجل هذه القضية.
But when it comes to our cities
ولكن حينما يتعلق الأمر بمدننا
and thinking about how death fits in our cities,
وكيفية التكيف مع فكرة الموت في مدننا،
there's much less regulation and design and thought
تتضاءل القوانين والتصاميم والأفكار
than we might imagine.
أكثر من ما نتخيل.
So we're not thinking about this,
إذا نحن لا نفكر حيال هذا الأمر،
but all of the people we imagine are thinking about it --
بل أن الناس الذين نتخيل أنهم يفكرون فيه
they're not taking care of it either.
هم لا يولون الأمر اهتمامًا حتى.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)